Guide to the Western Americana Collection of Miscellaneous Financial Materials Concerning Oil Companies Operating in the North American West
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Miscellaneous financial materials concerning oil companies operating in the North American West
1865-1956
Ndy36
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.34
(16 boxes)
This collection, compiled by William H. Brown, contains a variety of financial documents concerning oil companies operating in the North American West. Examples of these documents include informational pamphlets, company magazines, fact sheets, maps, memorandums, newspaper clippings, press releases, company correspondence, reports and analyses, letters to the stockholders, stockholder resolutions, petitions for secondary stock offerings, bond offerings, subscription forms, proxy statements, prospectuses, election forms, mortgage and trust indentures, deposit and trust agreements, reorganization plans and agreements, consolidation plans, and court documents. While all of these documents are represented in the collection, they are not all represented by each company.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Most of these financial materials were part of a collection acquired by Yale in 1922 from William H. Brown of West Haven, Conn. The collection, initially called the William H. Brown Statistical Library, numbered some 23,000 documents and covered the years 1890 to 1917. The collection was merged with similar materials already in the University Library and later expanded by gifts from Brown and others to become what is now known as the William H. Brown Collection.
Scope and Contents
This collection, compiled by William H. Brown, contains a variety of financial documents concerning oil companies operating in the North American West. Examples of these documents include informational pamphlets, company magazines, fact sheets, maps, memorandums, newspaper clippings, press releases, company correspondence, reports and analyses, letters to the stockholders, stockholder resolutions, petitions for secondary stock offerings, bond offerings, subscription forms, proxy statements, prospectuses, election forms, mortgage and trust indentures, deposit and trust agreements, reorganization plans and agreements, consolidation plans, and court documents. While all of these documents are represented in the collection, they are not all represented by each company.
Arrangement
Trade organizations, government agencies and other industry-related entities are listed first, after which oil companies are arranged in call number order. While this usually produces an alphabetical listing by company name, in some cases a change in a company name results in an out-of-sequence listing; thus, Continental Oil Company is found where its earlier name, Marland Oil Company, would have appeared.
Petroleum industry and trade -- West (U.S.); Financial statements -- Specimens.; Proxy statements -- Specimens.; Trust indentures -- Specimens.; Amerada Corporation; American Petroleum Industries Committee; Invincible Oil Corporation; Lewis Oil Corporation; Shaffer Oil and Refining Company; Shell Union Oil Corporation; Texon Oil and Land Company; William H. Brown Collection
- Trade Organizations and Government Agencies, 1920-1944; Ndy36 U2 +1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Petroleum Institute, 1920-1933, undated; (3 documents) (Box 1)
  - Petroleum Administration for War, 1944; (2 documents) (Box 1)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1922; (1 document) (Box 1)
  - American Oil Burner Association, 1931; (1 document) (Box 1)
  - Unidentified petroleum industry group, 1941?; (1 document) (Box 1)
- Amerada Corporation, 1926-1930; Ndy36 U2 +Am2; (3 documents) (Box 1, Folder 2)
- American Fuel Oil and Transportation Company, 1923-1926; Ndy36 U2 +Am3; (4 documents) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- American Petroleum Industries Committee, 1935-1944; Ndy36 U2 +Am46; (12 documents) (Box 1, Folder 4)
- American Republics Corporation, 1922-1927; Ndy36 U2 +Am48; (2 documents) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Associated Oil Company, 1917-1923; Ndy36 U2 +As7; (6 documents) (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Atlas Petroleum Corporation, 1919; Ndy36 U2 +At81; (2 documents) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- California Petroleum Company, 1865-1866; Ndy36 U2 +C118; (2 documents) (Box 1, Folder 8)
- California Petroleum Corporation, 1912-1928; Ndy36 U2 +C12
  - Financial history, 1915-1928; (10 documents) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Economic aspects, 1912; (2 documents) (Box 1, Folder 10)
- California Ryan Process Refinery, 1923; Ndy36 U2 +C129; (1 document) (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Central Fuel Oil Company, 1912-1913; Ndy36 U2 +C34; (3 documents) (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Central Petroleum Company, 1913-1919; Ndy36 U2 +C35; (2 documents) (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Cities Service Refining Company, 1923-1933; Ndy36 U2 +C49; (3 documents) (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Continental Oil Company (of Colorado), 1923-1924; Ndy36 U2 +C768; (4 documents) (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Continental Oil Company (Maine), 1924-1937; Ndy36 U2 +C77; (4 documents) (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Cosden Petroleum Corporation, 1932-1937; Ndy36 U2 +C82; (2 documents) (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Cosden Oil and Gas Company, 1917; Ndy36 U2 +C83; (7 documents) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Scope and Contents
  Included are documents from Cosden and Company (Delaware).
  Related Archival Materials note
  See Sinclair Consolidated Oil Corporation for a market comparison between Sinclair and Cosden.
- Crew Levick Company, 1921-1931; Ndy36 U2 +C86; (3 documents) (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Crown Central Petroleum Company, 1926-1930; Ndy36 U2 +C864; (2 documents) (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Crown Oil and Refining Company, 1919; Ndy36 U2 +C865; (1 document) (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Crystal Oil Refining Corporation, 1931; Ndy36 U2 +C889; (1 document) (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Darby Petroleum Corporation, 1919-1922; Ndy36 U2 +D24; (2 documents) (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Dixie Gulf Gas Company, 1927-1937; Ndy36 U2 +D64; (2 documents) (Box 2, Folder 4)
- El Dorado Refining Company, 1925-1927; Ndy36 U2 +El23; (5 documents) (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Empire Oil and Refining Company, 1927; Ndy36 U2 +Em68; (1 document) (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Empire Oil Purchasing Company, 1921; Ndy36 U2 +Em7; (2 documents) (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Empire Refining Company, 1917-1927; Ndy36 U2 +Em8; (2 documents) (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Galena-Signal Oil Company (Pennsylvania), 1913-1928; Ndy36 U2 +G13; (20 documents) (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Galena-Signal Oil Company (of Texas), 1933; Ndy36 U2 +G14; (1 document) (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Gates Oil Company, 1920; Ndy36 U2 +G22; (1 document) (Box 2, Folder 11)
- General Petroleum Company (San Francisco, Calif.), 1915-1923; Ndy36 U2 +G28; (7 documents) (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- General Petroleum Corporation, 1916-1925; Ndy36 U2 +G29; (8 documents) (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Gilliland Oil Company, 1921-1923; Ndy36 U2 +G41; (2 documents) (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Glenrock Oil Company, Incorporated, 1917-1925; Ndy36 U2 +G48; (5 documents) (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Globe Oil Company, 1918-1919; Ndy36 U2 +G51; (4 documents) (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Great Western Petroleum Company, 1919; Ndy36 U2 +G79; (1 document) (Box 3, Folder 7)
- J. M. Gufffey Petroleum Company, 1902-1906; Ndy36 U2 +G94; (4 documents) (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Gulf Oil Corporation (New Jersey), 1919-1933; Ndy36 U2 +G95; (10 documents) (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Gulf Oil Corporation of Pennsylvania, 1922-1928; Ndy36 U2 +G951; (9 documents) (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Holly Oil Company, 1937; Ndy36 U2 +H729; (1 document) (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Home Oil Refining Company of Texas, 1919-1920; Ndy36 U2 +H752; (4 documents) (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Houston Oil Company of Texas, 1901-1950; Ndy36 U2 +H81
  - 46 documents (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
  - 1 document (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Humble Oil and Refining Company, 1921-1937; Ndy36 U2 +H88; (9 documents) (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Independent Oil and Gas Company, 1923-1927; Ndy36 U2 +In17; (5 documents) (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Indiahoma Refining Company, 1920-1924; Ndy36 U2 +In2; (9 documents) (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Invincible Oil Corporation, 1919-1924; Ndy36 U2 +In9; (5 documents) (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Island Refining Corporation, 1919?-1924; Ndy36 U2 +Is4; (9 documents) (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Kirby Petroleum Company, 1921, 1922?; Ndy36 U2 +K63; (3 documents) (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Knickerbocker-Wyoming Oil Company, 1917?; Ndy36 U2 +K74; (1 document) (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Lewis Oil Corporation, 1927; Ndy36 U2 +L585; (3 documents) (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Liberty Oil Company Incorporated, 1921; Ndy36 U2 +L615; (1 document) (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Lion Oil Refining Company, 1925; Ndy36 U2 +L66; (1 document) (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Livingston Oil Corporation (of Delaware), 1920-1925; Ndy36 U2 +L75; (3 documents) (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Louisiana Land and Exploration Company, 1936; Ndy36 U2 +L928; This document is an extensive report in typescript encompassing physical, financial and production information on the company in 1936. Maps and hand-drawn diagrams are included.; (1 document) (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Louisiana Oil Refining Corporation, 1917-1935; Ndy36 U2 +L93; (7 documents) (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Magnolia Petroleum Company, 1912-1943; Ndy36 U2 +M28; (6 documents) (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Continental Oil Company, 1921-1951; Ndy36 U2 +M34; (28 documents) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  Included are documents from the Marland Oil Company.
- Meridian Petroleum Corporation, 1921-1922; Ndy36 U2 +M543; (3 documents) (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Mid-Continent Petroleum Corporation, 1916-1930; Ndy36 U2 +M591; (15 documents) (Box 5, Folder 13)
  Included are documents from Cosden and Company.
- Middle States Oil Corporation, 1920-1929; Ndy36 U2 +M593; (38 documents) (Box 5, Folder 14)
- National Oil Company, 1912-1922; Ndy36 U2 +N21; (8 documents) (Box 6, Folder 1)
- New National Oil Company, 1928; Ndy36 U2 +N423; (1 document) (Box 6, Folder 2)
- New York Oil Company (of Wyoming), 1921-1928; Ndy36 U2 +N424; (7 documents) (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Newblock Oil Company, 1923; Ndy36 U2 +N43; (1 document) (Box 6, Folder 4)
- North Central Texas Oil Company, Incorporated, 1926; Ndy36 U2 +N81; (1 document) (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Pacific Northwest Pipeline Corporation, 1955; Ndy36 U2 +P11; (1 document) (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Pacific Oil Company, 1926-1930; Ndy36 U2 +P12; (7 documents) (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Pan American Petroleum Company (of California), 1925; Ndy36 U2 +P18; (2 documents) (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Panhandle Producing and Refining Company, 1919-1943; Ndy36 U2 +P194; (9 documents) (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Petroleum Corporation of America, 1929; Ndy36 U2 +P44; (1 document) (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Phillips Petroleum Company, 1919-1956; Ndy36 U2 +P54
  - Financial history, 1919-1951; (30 documents) (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Economic aspects, 1933-1956; (11 documents) (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Pierce Oil Corporation, 1914-1926; Ndy36 U2 +P61; (55 documents) (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
- Producers and Refiners Corporation, 1919-1923; Ndy36 U2 +P94; (22 documents) (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Pure Oil Company, 1916-1941; Ndy36 U2 +P96; (26 documents) (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  Included are documents from the Ohio Cities Gas Company.
- Record Oil and Refining Company, 1919; Ndy36 U2 +R245; (1 document) (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Reiter-Foster Oil Corporation, 1925; Ndy36 U2 +R278; (1 document) (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Republic Oil and Refining Company, 1920; Ndy36 U2 +R29; (2 documents) (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Republic Petroleum Company, 1941; Ndy36 U2 +R299; (2 documents) (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Richfield Oil Company of California, 1926-1937; Ndy36 U2 +R41; (16 documents) (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Salt Creek Producers Association, Incorporated, 1920-1927; Ndy36 U2 +Sa3; (12 documents) (Box 9, Folder 7-8)
  Included in the collection are three copies of the "First Report of Advisory committee," two of which contain large field maps.
- Santa Fe Oil and Refining Company, 1923; Ndy36 U2 +Sa6; (2 documents) (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Sapulpa Refining Company, 1921; Ndy36 U2 +Sa7; (1 document) (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Seaboard Oil and Gas Company, 1922; Ndy36 U2 +Se1; (4 documents) (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Shaffer Oil and Refining Company, 1919-1934; Ndy36 U2 +Sh2; (15 documents) (Box 9, Folder 12)
  Included are documents from the Deep Rock Oil Corporation.
- Shamrock Oil and Gas Corporation, 1936-1944; Ndy36 U2 +Sh22; (6 documents) (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Shell Union Oil Corporation, 1922-1947; Ndy36 U2 +Sh4; (37 documents) (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Simms Petroleum Company, 1922-1935; Ndy36 U2 +Si4; (7 documents) (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Sinclair Consolidated Oil Corporation, 1919-1951; Ndy36 U2 +Si6; (68 documents) (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
  Included are documents from the Consolidated Oil Corporation.
  Included in the collection are several glossy illustrated company magazines.
- Stanolind Crude Oil Purchasing Company, 1922-1928; Ndy36 U2 +Si61; (4 documents) (Box 10, Folder 3)
  Included are documents by the Sinclair Crude Oil Purchasing Company.
- Sinclair Gulf Corporation, 1917-1918; Ndy36 U2 +Si62; (6 documents) (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Sinclair Oil and Refining Corporation, 1916-1922; Ndy36 U2 +Si66; (13 documents) (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Sinclair Refining Company, 1918; Ndy36 U2 +Si67; (2 documents) (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Skelly Oil Company, 1921-1936; Ndy36 U2 +Sk2; (5 documents) (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Standard Oil Company (California), 1914-1950; Ndy36 U2 +St12; (38 documents) (Box 13, Folder 2-3)
- Standard Oil Company (Kansas), 1940; Ndy36 U2 +St16; (1 document) (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Standard Oil Company of Nebraska, 1935; Ndy36 U2 +St2; (1 document) (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Texas Company (Texas), 1908-1926; Ndy36 U2 +T28; (36 documents) (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Texas Corporation, 1929-1951; Ndy36 U2 +T281
  Documents with the Texas Company logo do not refer to the original Texas Company (Texas), which was dissolved in 1927, but rather to one of the many subsidiaries of the Texas Corporation.
  - Financial history, 1929-1951; (20 documents) (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Economic aspects, 1930-1944; (8 documents) (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Texas Pacific Coal and Oil Company, 1919; Ndy36 U2 +T29; (1 document) (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Texon Oil and Land Company (of Delaware), 1928; Ndy36 U2 +T314; (1 document) (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Tide Water Oil Company, 1916-1926; Ndy36 U2 +T43; (14 documents) (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Transcontinental Oil Company, 1919-1930; Ndy36 U2 +T68; (17 documents) (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Trinity Oil Corporation, 1919; Ndy36 U2 +T73; (1 document) (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Union Oil Company of California, 1908-1949; Ndy36 U2 +Un2; (27 documents) (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
- United Oil Company, 1924-1926; Ndy36 U2 +Un58; (3 documents) (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Waters Pierce Oil Company, 1912; Ndy36 U2 +W29; (1 document) (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Western Oil Fields Corporation, 1921-1922; Ndy36 U2 +W52; (2 documents) (Box 16, Folder 5)
- White Eagle Oil and Refining Company, 1919-1928; Ndy36 U2 +W58; (6 documents) (Box 16, Folder 6)
- H. F. Wilcox Oil and Gas Company, 1928; Ndy36 U2 +W64; (1 document) (Box 16, Folder 7)